Guide to the Josephine Steiner Barger Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Josephine Steiner Barger papers
1912-1984
MS 1729
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.25
The papers consist of correspondence, clippings, photographs, and memorabilia documenting the personal and professional life of Josephine Steiner Barger.
Barger, Josephine Steiner, 1913-1971
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James D. Barger, 1997; M. Susan Barger, 2002-2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series and two additions: I. Topical Files, 1913-1984. II. Photographic Materials, 1912-1969.
Biographical / Historical
Josephine Steiner was born in Bluffton, Ohio, in 1913 to Dr. Josiah and Augusta Steiner. Her father served in the medical branch of the Army in World War I. She was raised as a Mennonite and graduated from Bluffton High School and Bluffton College in 1930 and 1932, respectively. In 1934 Steiner earned her B.A. degree from Ohio University. She then attended Yale School of Nursing, where she received a Master of Nursing degree in 1938. When World War II began, Steiner joined the 39th General Hospital, a medical unit which was formed of Yale graduates. She served the war effort in New Zealand, Saipan, and Guadalcanal. From 1946 to 1949 Steiner was superintendent of nurses at Lake Maracaibo Hospital in Venezuela. She returned to the United States in 1949 and earned a Master of Science in Nursing degree from Western Reserve University in Cleveland, Ohio in 1951. Steiner later became superintendent of nurses and director of nursing at Good Samaritan Hospital in Phoenix, Arizona. In 1952 she married Dr. James D. Barger; thereafter they moved to Las Vegas, Nevada. The Bargers had two children, Michael Thomas and Mary Elizabeth, and also adopted James D., Jr. and Mary Susan. Barger died in 1971.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, clippings, photographs, and memorabilia documenting the personal and professional life of Josephine Steiner Barger.
Military hospitals; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work; World War, 1939-1945 -- Women -- United States; Barger, Josephine Steiner, 1913-1971; Good Samaritan Hospital (Phoenix, Ariz.); Yale University. School of Nursing
- Topical Files, 1913-1984; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged in alphabetical order by topic, and consists of correspondence, clippings, and professional and personal documents.
  - Arizona [Good Samaritan Hospital], 1952-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Childhood, 1913, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Death and estate, 1970-1972, 1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Education
    - Youth [Bluffton High School, Bluffton College], 1926, 1929-1930, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Ohio University, 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Western Reserve University, 1950-1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Yale School of Nursing, 1935-1942, 1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Marriage and family, 1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Steiner, Josiah S. [Father]
    - Death, 1943-1944, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - World War I correspondence, 1918, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Venezuela, 1946-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - World War II
    - Army, 1942-1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1942-1947, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 39th General Hospital, 1943-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous, 1942-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - Miscellaneous [Social Security card, bank account record 1955 planner, Bluffton News], 1942, 1945, 1949-1952, 1955, 1966, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Photographic Materials, 1912-1969; Series II
  The series is arranged by type. It consists of photographs, slides, and photograph albums recording the personal and professional life of Josephine Steiner Barger. The photographs section is arranged in alphabetical order by topic. The photograph albums and slides sections contain pictures of friends, vacations, her professional environment, and local life from the South Pacific in World War II and Venezuela from 1942 to 1949.
  - Photographs
    - Arizona [Good Samaritan Hospital], 1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bluffton High School
      - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Yearbooks, 1928, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Childhood and early family, 1912-1924, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Late portrait of J.S.B., 1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Venezuela, 1946-1947, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - World War II, 1944, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Yale School of Nursing, 1946, 1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Photograph albums, undated (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
  - Slides, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-105
  - Biographical and genealogical material regarding Josephine Steiner Barger, James Daniel Barger, and Josiah Steiner and family, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Baumgartner, Bonnie Steiner, 1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Dilley, Geneva Steiner and family, 1969-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Hoff, Fern Irvin, 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Steiner, Augusta Irvin, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal papers
    - Calling cards from Bluffton, Ohio High School, Class of 1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Playbills, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Postcard folios, 1919, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs
    - Barger-Steiner wedding and honeymoon, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 9 - 10)
    - Elementary school and high school photographs of Josephine Steiner Barger, [ca. 1920], 1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Family, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - World War II [39th General Hospital, New Zealand, and other views of the Pacific, [ca. 1944] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - World War II
    - Maps of Guadalcanal Island, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Songbook, [ca. 1944] (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Additional Material, Accession 2003-M-085
  - Passport of Josephine Steiner Barger, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, correspondence, and other miscellaneous papers relating to Lucia Allyn and Dr. Clarence Robbins., 1971-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 39th General Hospital, List of Home Addresses of Male Officers, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)